all right
[Music]
in my videos on t i caution not to drink
with meals because he can inhibit the
absorption of iron from Foods anywhere
from 26 to 99 percent perhaps depending
on the Brewing time brand how strong it
is what about the inhibition of food
iron absorption by coffee
I was first looking this up I ran across
this study on the effects of
discontinuing coffee intake on the iron
status of Guatemalan toddlers thinking
they must be talking about like
breastfeeding mothers or something but
no coffee is one of the first liquids
given to infants in Guatemala I did not
know that anyway the inhibition of food
iron absorption by coffee a cup of
coffee reduced iron absorption from a
hamburger meal by 39 percent as opposed
to a 64 decrease with tea so not as bad
as tea but still significant blockage
and just like with the tea the stronger
the coffee the more our iron absorption
was impeded in terms of timing no
decrease in Iron absorption occurred
when coffee was consumed an hour before
a meal but waiting an hour after meal to
drink the coffee didn't seem to help
which can be probably explained by the
fact that it may take up to nearly two
hours to clear a meal from the stomach
so starting an hour in the coffee can
catch up to the food
now you can reverse the effect of tear
coffee by adding orange juice to a meal
or even better in orange or any source
of vitamin C rich food the vitamin C
boosts iron absorption which is good for
people who are borderline anemic but for
many the blockage of iron absorption
from coffee may actually be a good thing
iron is a double-edged sword on the one
hand iron is essential element vital for
blood production on the other hand iron
is a potent pro-oxidant so maybe the
reduced risk of type 2 diabetes
associated with coffee consumption is
due to the inhibition of iron absorption
by coffee see the risk of type 2
diabetes increases with the increase in
the amount of ferritin in your blood
which is a measure of your iron stores
so higher iron stores higher diabetes
risk same thing with the risk of
gestational diabetes during pregnancy so
you need to make sure you're getting
enough iron but not building up too much
iron in your body
how do we know it's cause and effect
because if you randomize diabetics like
old-fashioned bloodletting but instead
of leeches they just donate blood a
couple times to lower their iron stores
and those in the blood donation group
had better blood sugar control better
insulin secretion less insulin
resistance and iron depletion improves
artery dysfunction in type 2 diabetics
as well
same thing with gout does inhibition of
iron absorption by coffee reduce the
risk of gout let's find out near iron
deficiency induced remission of gouty
arthritis they took gout patients and
maintained their iron Source at the
lowest level possible without causing
anemia and gouty attacks markedly
diminished in every patient with effects
ranging from a complete remission to a
marked reduction of incidence and
severity of Gaudi attacks here's the
attack rates before and after
so maybe that's one reason coffee
consumption is associated with lower
risk of gout it blocks some of the iron
uptake
increasing evidence suggests that iron
is also involved in multiple diseases of
Aging including Alzheimer's disease
Parkinson's disease and heart disease in
terms of iron and Alzheimer's they think
it's iron's potential to effectively
rust brain tissue by producing free
radicals that may cause
neurodegeneration contributing to
Alzheimer's disease pathology at
numerous levels so much so there's an
interest in trying to treat Alzheimer's
Disease by targeting iron
high body iron stores may also be
associated with shorter telomeres which
is a biomarker of biological aging and
for those of you thinking well I mean if
I had high iron stores I'd probably know
about it only five percent of patients
with elevated iron report ever being
told by a doctor that this was the case
to prevent too much iron accumulation
regularly drinking tea with meals will
do it found to decrease the amount of
bloodletting you have to do for people
with a genetic iron overload disease but
you'd want to do the opposite drink tea
only apart from meals if you were at
risk for iron deficiency anemia
besides tea and coffee there are other
beverages that can block iron absorption
peppermint is right up there with black
tea chocolate milk would do it too and
chamomile blocks iron about in the same
range as coffee so if your iron stores
are high these are great meal time
choices if you're struggling to get
enough iron you wouldn't want to
regularly drink these with meals
we think it's the polyphenol
phytonutrients so what about herbs and
spices they're packed with polyphenol
goodness now this study was done
basically in a test tube not in real
people but there is this case report of
iron deficiency anemia due to high dose
turmeric a physician treated himself for
an osteoarthritis flare with capsules of
turmeric extract and he was anemic
couldn't get his iron up despite taking
iron supplements but two weeks after
stopping the turmeric his blood count
iron levels were all back to normal so
on one hand those presenting to doctors
offices with iron deficiency anemia
should be asked about supplement use at
the same time the ability of turmeric to
glom onto intestinal iron may lead it to
being useful in states of iron overload
foreign